<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::eckstru.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-2014115</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
Ruth Eckstein papers, 1962-1981

</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Hannah Jenkins, 2013</author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2013">
2014</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Greg Kinney, 
<date>2014</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
<descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
</profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2014-08-14</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2010 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
Ruth Eckstein Papers, 1962-1981</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Hannah Jenkins, 2013</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">
Eckstein, Ruth
</persname>
</origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
Ruth Eckstein papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1962-1981
</unitdate>

<unitdate type="bulk" encodinganalog="245$g">
1962-1974
</unitdate>

</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
0.4 linear feet
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
2014115 Aa 2
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
Ruth Eckstein served as a counselor at the University of Michigan from 1967-1981, and her research focused on minority and underprivileged students at the University and in the Ann Arbor area. The collection primarily contains information on the research topics that Eckstein pursued in the Ann Arbor area. The collection spans from 1962-1981 with the bulk of the material being from 1962-1974.
</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
The collection was donated by Bob Eckstein (Donor No. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">10665</num>) in November 2011. 
</p></acqinfo>

<accruals encodinganalog="584"><p>
No further additions to the papers are expected.
</p></accruals>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>
The collection is open to research.
</p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
Ruth Eckstein papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>



</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>Ruth Eckstein earned her B.A. in Sociology at the University of Wisconsin. She did her graduate work at the School of Social Service Administration at the University of Chicago. She then became a member of the American Association of Social Workers. Eckstein first worked as a family caseworker, but later shifted to vocational counseling. From 1967-1969 she served as a counselor at the Counseling Center at the University of Michigan. She then moved to the position of Academic Counselor for the Rackham Graduate School and the Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs, from 1970-1971 and 1979-1980 respectively. Between these jobs, Eckstein served as a program analyst for the Opportunity Program through the Office of the Vice-President for Student Affairs from 1971-1981 and in 1975 she became a certified social worker. During this time, outside of the University, she worked as a vocational counselor in private practice and as a consultant for the Child and Family Service of Washtenaw County in Ann Arbor. In 1981, she left the University so she could expand her private practice and she became a consultant in vocational counseling to the Child and Family Service group of Washtenaw County. </p>

<p>Her early research involved studies of students recommended for counseling from the Ann Arbor area schools. As a social worker, she attempted to provide vocational, career, and academic counseling, including assisting people with job preparation and finding. While at the University, Eckstein worked on designing and developing research strategies for projects related to selected aspects of academic performance problems and progress of undergraduate students. Her counseling and research at this time was primarily focused on minority students. </p>

<p>She was married to Alexander Eckstein, the Chairman of the National Committee on United States-China Relations and professor of economics and specialist on China at the University of Michigan. They had one son, Robert Eckstein, who was born in 1951.</p>

</bioghist>



<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>The Ruth Eckstein papers contain bibliographical information as well as correspondence to and from Eckstein. There is also information on the United Fund and Community Services organization which Eckstein worked with for a short time. The collection contains two series: Personal, Research, and Youth Programs in Ann Arbor.</p></scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Eckstein, Ruth.</persname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Minorities--Education--Michigan.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Social service--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills.</corpname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. Opportunity Award Program.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">


<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Personal</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Personal series contains biographical information and some scattered correspondence. </p></scopecontent><c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Bibliographical Information</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1965</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">1971-1974</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">1981</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Research</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Research series contains files regarding Eckstein's research into black and minority student enrollment at the University of Michigan, and research on the effectiveness of the Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills (CULS) classes that the University offered. Various writings that she produced are also included, as well as student files from counseling cases she worked on and information on the Opportunity Program at the University where she did research and worked as a program analyst. The Vocational-Counseling Program was a research project that Eckstein worked on that offered counseling to students in need, as well as a project designed to analyze the current help that the students could receive from the school district. </p></scopecontent><c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Black Student Enrollment, <unitdate type="inclusive">1971-1973</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills (CULS) Classes, <unitdate type="inclusive">1974-1976</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>2 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Minority Student Enrollment, <unitdate type="inclusive">1971-1973</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Opportunity Program, <unitdate type="inclusive">1969-1974</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Writings</unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Youth Programs in Ann Arbor, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1965</unitdate></unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Youth Programs of Ann Arbor series documents a project Eckstein assisted with that looked at what recreational opportunities were available for the youth in Ann Arbor and how these programs could be improved so that they appealed to a broader range of youth.</p></scopecontent><c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Final Report</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Graphs</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Notes</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>United Fund and Community Services, <unitdate type="inclusive">1962-1964</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01> 

</dsc></archdesc>

</ead>
