<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead><eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core"><eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="-//us::MiU-H//TEXT us::MiU-H::gasspub.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">umich-bhl-97133</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt>
<titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for Gilbert and Sullivan Society (University of Michigan), <date>1947-</date></titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid prepared by Marilyn McNitt </author></titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher><date encodinganalog="Date">2002</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by Greg Kinney, <date>November, 2002</date></creation>
<langusage>The finding aid is written in  <language encodinganalog="Language" langcode="eng">English.</language></langusage></profiledesc>

<revisiondesc>
<change><date>20070406</date><item>minor update with new accessions</item></change>
<change><date>20050127</date><item>updated with new accessions</item></change>
<change><date>20031010</date><item>Converted to EAD2002 using Word macro and Xmetal</item></change>
<change><date>20021126</date><item>Original encoding in EAD ver. 1.0 from Word 6.0 file using word macros and manual tagging in A/E.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter>
<titlepage><publisher>University Archives and Records Program<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher><titleproper>Finding Aid for <lb/>Gilbert and Sullivan Society <lb/>(University of Michigan)<lb/>Publications, 1958-</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid prepared by: <lb/>Marilyn McNitt</author></titlepage></frontmatter>

<archdesc audience="external" type="inventory" level="recordgrp" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110">
University of Michigan.  Gilbert and Sullivan Society.
</corpname></origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">Gilbert and Sullivan Society (University of Michigan), publications

<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1958-3999" encodinganalog="245$f">1947-ongoing </unitdate></unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">2 linear ft.</extent></physdesc>


<abstract>Publications  of University of Michigan organization which produces Gilbert and Sullivan operettas, including flyers, newsletters and a history of the organization.</abstract>

<unitid countrycode="us" repositorycode="MiU-H" encodinganalog="099" type="call number">97133 Bimu F71 2</unitid>

<langmaterial>The materials are in <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">English.</language></langmaterial>

<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea> University of Michigan</corpname><extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>Publications have been received from Harry Benford (donor # <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">3123</num>) and are received periodically from the unit (donor #<num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e"> 8613</num>).</p></acqinfo>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>The publications are open for research.</p>

<p><extptr href="uarpacc" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></userestrict>

<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>item, folder title, box no., Gilbert and Sullivan Society (University of Michigan) publications, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite></descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><p>The University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (UMGASS) traces its origins to the fall of 1946, when University of Michigan freshman Gloria Katlan (later Bennish) called a campus-wide meeting for those interested in the production of a Gilbert and Sullivan operetta.  Organizational concerns occupied the Society's attention for the first year, and it was not until the fall of 1947 that members staged a first performance of the Mikado.  Since that date, the Society has produced at least two operettas each year, going through the repertoire of thirteen Gilbert and Sullivan operettas every six or seven years. </p>
<p>UMGASS is an officially recognized University of Michigan student organization, but membership is not limited to students.  Any interested person may participate in UMGASS productions or hold office in the Society.  Under conditions set by its constitution, UMGASS business is managed by a small governing board elected annually by active participants in the productions.  The board selects each year's directors and selects and produces the shows.  Since 1969, UMGASS has been encouraged and supported by a group called the Friends of the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (FUMGASS).  Chief among FUMGASS's activities has been the production of a journal of Gilbert and Sullivan news and events, both on the University of Michigan campus and worldwide.  The journal's acronym, GASBAG, stands for Gilbert and Sullivan Boys and Girls.</p>
<p>Professor Harry Benford, of the Department of Naval Architecture, and his wife have served as UMGASS faculty advisors since 1956.  They were particularly active during the years 1962-1982 and were instrumental in the formation of FUMGASS.  Professor Benford served as GASBAG editor from 1969 through 1982, when he and his wife retired from the University. </p></bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520"><p>The Publications series (2 linear feet) includes flyers, programs, newsletters, and a history of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society as well as the newsletter of the Friends of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society.  The publications are divided into two series:  Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications.</p></scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p>

<controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society.</corpname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society. Friends.</corpname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.</corpname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="710">University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society. Friends.</corpname><title encodinganalog="740">Pudding full of plums.</title></controlaccess>

<controlaccess><head>Genre/Form:</head><genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Histories.</genreform><genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Newsletters.</genreform><genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Programs.</genreform></controlaccess></controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined"><c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Unit Publications</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Unit Publications series includes flyers announcing future productions, ticket prices, and casts.  There is also a history entitled <title render="italic">A Pudding Full of Plums:  The University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society's First Fifty Years</title> by long-time advisor Harry Benford.  It was published in 1997 to commemorate the fiftieth anniversary of the society.  This series also includes programs, dating from 1958 to the present, of the various operettas produced in Ann Arbor and other locations in the state by the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society.</p></scopecontent><c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Brochures, <unitdate type="inclusive">1972-2005</unitdate> and <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Flyers, <unitdate type="inclusive">1990-1995</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><unittitle>Histories</unittitle></did>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><title render="italic">A Pudding Full of Plums:  The University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society's First Fifty Years</title> by Harry Benford, <unitdate type="inclusive">1997</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Programs, <unitdate type="inclusive">1947-2011</unitdate> and <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>47 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>UMGASS 50th Anniversary Memory Book, <unitdate type="inclusive">1997</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Sub-Unit Publications</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Sub-Unit Publications subseries includes the newsletter The Gasbag published by the Friends of the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (FUMGASS).  The Bentley Historical Library has a complete run of this publication from 1969 to the present.</p></scopecontent><c02 level="file"><did><unittitle>Friends of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society</unittitle></did>
<c03 level="file"><did><unittitle>Newsletters</unittitle></did>
<c04 level="file"><did><unittitle><title render="italic">The Gasbag</title></unittitle></did>
<c05 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Vol. 1-10, <unitdate type="inclusive">1969-1979</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>10 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c05>
<c05 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle>Vol. 11-39, <unitdate type="inclusive">1979-2011</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>28 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c05></c04></c03></c02></c01> 
</dsc>

</archdesc></ead> 
