<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::giltrowd.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-2013124</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
David Giltrow photograph collection, 1960-1961

</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Brian Williams, October 2013</author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2013">
2013</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Greg Kinney, 
<date>2013</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
<descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
</profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2013-10-28</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2007 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
David Giltrow photograph collection, 1960-1961</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Brian Williams, October 2013</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">
Giltrow, David
</persname>
</origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
David Giltrow photograph collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1960-1961
</unitdate>
</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
0.2 linear feet
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
2013124 Aa 2
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
David Giltrow was a student photographer for <title render="italic">The Michigan Daily</title> and <title render="italic">Michiganensian</title> from 1960 to 1961.   The collection contains negatives and paper contact prints of photos taken by Giltrow. Subjects include John F. Kennedy's 1960 campaign stop in Ann Arbor and whistle stop train trip in Michigan, campus visits by Pat Kennedy Lawford and Chester Bowles, a Pete Seeger concert, Americans Committed to World Responsibility Conference, and a 1961 Ann Arbor Civil Rights march. 
</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
by David Giltrow (Donor <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">10261</num>) in October 2013.
</p></acqinfo>

<accruals encodinganalog="584"><p>
No further additions to the collection are expected.
</p></accruals>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>
The collection is open without restriction
</p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
David Giltrow photograph collection, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>

<processinfo><p>[Delete this set of tags if not needed for digital material processing]</p>
<p><extptr href="digitalproc" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p>
</processinfo>

</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>David Giltrow graduated from the University of Michigan in 1961. While a student, Giltrow worked as a photographer for the campus newspaper <title render="italic">The Michigan Daily</title> and the <title render="italic">Michiganensian</title> yearbook. He photographed the 1960 John F. Kennedy and Richard Nixon presidential campaigns for the<title render="italic">Michigan Daily</title> .  Upon graduation he joined the American Friends Service Committee as a volunteer in Tanzania, arriving just ahead of the first recruited Peace Corps group of civil engineers. Giltrow was assigned to the government film unit. Following his three year assignment, Giltrow enrolled at Syracuse University where he received a master's degree and Ph.D. degree in instructional technology. At Syracuse he served as a program assistant in Syracuse's Peace Corps training programs for Africans in the 1960s. Returning to Tanzania in 1969, he researched young Tanzanians' comprehension of motion picture elements. During this time he met Peggy Medina who was completing two years as a volunteer. Medina returned to Michigan to work on a library degree at the University of Michigan. They were married in Ann Arbor in 1971 when Giltrow returned to the United States.</p>

<p>After completing his doctorate, Giltrow went on to work in some 20 developing countries in Africa, Southeast Asia and the Middle East as an independent consultant in distance education, agricultural communications, community forestry and development projects for the United Nations, World Bank, and USAID.</p>
</bioghist>


<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>The David Giltrow photograph collection documents a selection of Giltrow's work as a photographer for the <title render="italic">Michigan Daily</title> and the <title render="italic">Michiganensian</title> from 1960 to 1961.  The collection consists of original 35mm negatives and paper contact prints. The negatives cover six notable campus visitors and events. The collection also contains a brief biography and a group portrait of <title render="italic">Michiganensian</title> photographers which includes Giltrow. </p>
</scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p>



<controlaccess><head>Subjects - Visual Materials:</head>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Giltrow, David.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Seeger, Pete, 1919-</persname>
<subject source="lctgm" encodinganalog="650">African Americans--Civil Rights.</subject>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Americans Committed to World Responsibility at the University of Michigan.</corpname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Ann Arbor (Mich.)</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Grand Rapids (Mich.)</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Kalamazoo (Mich.)</geogname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="630">Michigan daily.</subject>
<subject source="lctgm" encodinganalog="650">Political elections--1960.</subject>
<subject source="lctgm" encodinganalog="650">Political parades and rallies.</subject>

</controlaccess>




<controlaccess><head>Genre Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Photographs.</genreform>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">


<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Biography</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>Biography contains a brief biographical sketch of Giltrow's career.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Brief biography by Giltrow</unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Portraits</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>Portraits contains a portrait of Giltrow in the 1960s and a group photograph of the 1960 Michiganensian photographers which includes Giltrow and Fred Shippey along with David Newman, Mike Factor, Paul Krynicki, and Gerry Aronheim.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Print of <title render="italic">Michiganensian</title> photographers, <unitdate type="inclusive">1960</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Pat Kennedy Lawford</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>Pat Kennedy Lawford negatives documents the campus visit of Pat Kennedy Lawford, the sister of John F. Kennedy. Lawford visited Ann Arbor and met with supporters in the Michigan Union. G. Mennen Williams, the Governor of Michigan also spoke at the Michigan Union during the event.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Negatives of visit, <unitdate type="inclusive">October 1960</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>John F. Kennedy Whistle Stop Tour of Michigan</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>John F. Kennedy Whistle Stop Tour of Michigan includes negatives taken by Giltrow while covering Kennedy's campaign visit to Michigan for the<title render="italic">Michigan Daily</title> . Giltrow traveled with Kennedy's entourage of photographers and journalists on the whistle stop tour which was to travel through Jackson, Albion, Battle Creek, Kalamazoo and Grand Rapids before finishing at Lansing. This was reportedly the only whistle stop train tour of Kennedy's campaign. Michigan Governor G. Mennen Williams </p>

<p>Kennedy flew to Michigan following the televised debate with Richard M. Nixon, and landed at Willow Run Airport on October 13, 1960. Kennedy eventually made his way to the Michigan Union after midnight where he was greeted by thousands of students and supporters prompting an impromptu speech on the steps of the Union where he introduced the idea of the Peace Corps. On October 14, Kennedy left the Union and embarked on a train trip across Michigan. The negatives document Kennedy's speech at the Michigan Union, the crowd awaiting Kennedy, and his departure later that morning. </p>

<p>Several negatives of the whistle stop train trip document campaign stops in Grand Rapids and Kalamazoo. A reproduction of Kennedy's Michigan itinerary is included. It details times and anticipated schedules for Kennedy and his entourage.   </p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Negatives of campaign stops, <unitdate type="inclusive">October 1960</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Chester Bowles</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>Chester Bowles October 1960 visit to the University of Michigan is recorded in negatives of his presentation at the Michigan Union. Speaking on world affairs, Bowles was John F. Kennedy's foreign policy advisor. Bowles speech reportedly influenced Al and Judy Guskin who started a Peace Corps group at Michigan. </p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Negatives of visit, <unitdate type="inclusive">October 1960</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Pete Seeger</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>Pete Seeger Concert negatives show Seeger performing in the Winter of 1961 at Ann Arbor High School.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Negatives of concert at Ann Arbor High School, <unitdate type="inclusive">1961</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Americans Committed to World Responsibility Conference</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>Negatives of the March 1961 Americans Committed to World Responsibility Conference show <title render="italic">Michigan Daily</title> editor Tom Hayden, <title render="italic">Daily</title> night editor Phil Power and Sharon Jeffries, daughter of Democratic leader Millie Jeffries at the conference along with speakers Sargent Shriver and Hubert H. Humphrey. Henry Reuss, co-sponsor with Humphrey of Peace Corps type legislation, also spoke at the conference.  </p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Negatives of Conference, <unitdate type="inclusive">March 1961</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Ann Arbor Civil Rights  March </unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>Ann Arbor Civil Rights March negatives show a march and demonstration for Civil Rights in April 1961. The march was down State Street with speeches on the University of Michigan diag. Roger Seasonwein was the organizer for the march. </p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Negatives of  March, <unitdate type="inclusive">April 1961</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>
 

</dsc>


<descgrp type="add"><relatedmaterial><head>Related Material</head>
<p>Additional photographs from the same era may be found in the <title render="italic">Michigan Daily</title> records also held by the Bentley Historical Library.  The Frederick L. Shippey visual materials collection features the work of another <title render="italic">Michigan Daily</title> photographer covering the Kennedy campaign stop in Michigan. The Samuel F. Schneider photograph collection contains 15 prints of the Kennedy visit to Ann Arbor taken by Schneider, an independent photographer.</p>
</relatedmaterial></descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>
