<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::mortarbd.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-8917</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
Mortar Board, Pi Sigma Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan) records, 1906-2008 

</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Kate Donovan, June 2009</author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2009">
2009</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Greg Kinney, 
<date>2009</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage><descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules></profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2009-09-03</date><item>Original encoding from Word 6.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>University Archives and Records Program<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
Mortar Board, Pi Sigma Alpha Chapter <lb/>(University of Michigan) <lb/>records, 1906-2008 
</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Kate Donovan, June 2009
</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110">
Mortar Board (Society). Pi Sigma Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan)
</corpname></origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
Mortar Board, Pi Sigma Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan) records 
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1906-2008
</unitdate>

<unitdate type="bulk" encodinganalog="245$g">
1920-1956
</unitdate>
</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
0.5 linear feet
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
8917 Bimu F 41 2
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
University of Michigan chapter of the scholastic honorary society Mortar Board.  The bulk of the records date from the 1920s through the 1950s, and include organizational constitutions; membership rolls; treasury and project reports; press clippings; and organizational histories.
</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
The collection was acquired through David Mickey (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">10222</num>).
 
</p></acqinfo>

<accruals encodinganalog="584"><p>Periodic additions to the records expected.</p></accruals>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
<p>The collection is open without restriction.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
Mortar Board, Pi Sigma Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan) records , Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>
</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>The Society of the Mortarboard at the University of Michigan was founded in 1905 by four members of the class of 1906; Jane Cochrane, Anna Waugh, Effie Armstrong, and Sue Diack.  Conceived of as an honor society for senior women, the organization devoted itself to scholarship and service, with a commitment to school spirit at the university.</p>

<p>As one of only three female honor societies on campus, Mortarboard regularly worked alongside its fellow women's groups, the Senior Society and Scroll, to promote social events and advocate for campus concerns such as new women's dormitories, women's rest rooms, academic honesty and cheating, and financial assistance for female students.  From 1905 through 1917, Mortarboard operated as an independent honor society.  However, similar societies, many with the same name, formed at other colleges and universities during the same period.</p>

<p>In February 1918, Michigan's Mortarboard Society met with delegates from female collegiate senior honor societies from Cornell University, Ohio State University, Syracuse University, and Swathmore at the Syracuse campus to form a national organization.  Although the members from the Syracuse delegation declined to join the new group, the other members elected to form a national organization and adopted a pin, motto, and bylaws.  "Mortar Board" was chosen as the group's official name, and Pi Sigma Alpha as its Greek letters, during its second annual conference at the University of Michigan in 1919.  Mortar Board remained an all-women's organization until 1975 when it decided, as a result of Title IX, to become a coeducational society.</p>

<p>Still active as an honor society for seniors, the Michigan chapter of the Mortar Board Society lists among its accomplishments, a commitment to the advancement of women and women's education, ongoing support for a scholarship fund, support for female residence halls, and ongoing community service projects.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>The records of the Michigan chapter of Mortar Board span the years 1906 to 2008, but consist primarily of materials from 1920 through 1956.  The collection is organized under a single series; Administrative Materials.</p>

<p>The Administrative Materials series, 1906-2008 (0.5 linear feet), consists of organizational histories, annual reports, chapter and organizational governing documents, membership rolls, press clippings, as well as project, treasury, and presidents' reports.  The years covered in this series are scattered, with the bulk of the materials covering 1920-1956.</p>

<p>A history and record book details the work of the organization and its membership from 1906 to 1956.  The organizational histories trace Mortar Board's growth since its founding, and include annual reports for the following years: 1919-1923; 1926-1927; 1930-1935; 1938-1949; and 1951-1954.  In addition to a historical narrative and annual reports, the organizational history also includes information on the organization's songs and ritual activities.  The records also include membership rolls listing members for the years 1906-1948 and 1957-1962.  The membership rolls for 1906-1913 are found in both a membership book, as well as in the organizational history.  The presidents' reports, 1949-1956, detail activities during those years and include two photographs of Mortar Board members.</p>

</scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>

<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">University of Michigan -- Honorary societies.</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">Mortar Board (Society). Pi Sigma Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan).</corpname>


</controlaccess>










</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">

<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Administrative Materials</unittitle></did>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Constitutions, <unitdate type="inclusive">1946-1958</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>History, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1963</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>History and Record Book, <unitdate type="inclusive">1906-1956</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Membership Roll, <unitdate type="inclusive">1906-1913</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">1957-1962</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Money and Service Reports, <unitdate type="inclusive">1949-1966</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Presidents' Reports, 1949/50-1955-56 </unittitle></did> <note><p>(includes photographs)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Press Clippings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1955-1956</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Chapter Records, <unitdate type="inclusive">1997-2000</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">2008</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>

</dsc>
<descgrp><relatedmaterial><head>Related Material</head>
<p>Researchers should note that related material on the Mortar Board Society, also located at the Bentley Historical Library, may be found in the Mortar Board Alumnae Club, Ann Arbor Chapter records,1953-1973, as well as in <title render="italic">Unscrambling the Maize: Mortar Board's Guide to Student Life at the University of Michigan</title> by Members of Mortar Board Senior Honor Society, 1976-77, compiled and edited by Karen Ann Brzys. </p>

<p>Some related content appears in the records of Senior Society, a women's honorary society for unaffiliated women at the University of Michigan. </p>
</relatedmaterial></descgrp>
</archdesc>



</ead>
