<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::ringerw.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-2012119</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
William R. Ringer papers, 1920-1922

</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Brian Williams, August 2012</author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2012">
2012</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Greg Kinney, 
<date>2012</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
<descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
</profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2012-08-12</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2007 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
William R. Ringer papers, 1920-1922</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Brian Williams, August 2012</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>


<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">
Ringer, William Raimond, 1898-1973
</persname>
</origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
William R. Ringer papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1920-1922
</unitdate>
</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
0.3 linear feet
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
2012119 Aa 2
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
William R. Ringer was a student at the University of Michigan Law School from 1920 to 1922.  Collection consists of three volumes of detailed diary entries interspersed with ephemera collected while a student.
</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
The collection was received in January 2012 (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">10708</num>).  
</p></acqinfo>

<accruals encodinganalog="584"><p>
No further additions to the papers are expected.
</p></accruals>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>
The collection is open to research without restriction.
</p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
William R. Ringer papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>
</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>William Raimond Ringer was born August 11, 1898, in Williamsport, Indiana, to Victor and Alice Thomas Ringer.  He graduated as the valedictorian of Williamsport High School in 1916.  He entered Indiana University in 1916 and graduated in 1920 magna cum laude with an AB in philosophy. While at Indiana he was a private in the United States Students' Army Training Corps (SATC). </p>

 <p>Ringer entered the University of Michigan Law School in September 1920 and graduated in June 1922 with a JD degree.  His brother Horace was also studying at the University of Michigan (AB 1924, LLB 1926). Ringer practiced law in Williamsport with his father Victor H. Ringer, an 1894 graduate of the university of Michigan Law School, as Ringer and Ringer from 1922 to 1926.  He moved to Indianapolis in 1926 and was in private practice from 1926 to 1929.  From 1929 to 1931 he served as the Trial Deputy Prosecuting Attorney in Criminal Court in Marion County Indiana before returning to private practice. In 1937 Ringer joined the National Labor Relations Board as a Trial Examiner. He was Chief Trial Examiner from 1942 until his retirement in 1963.</p>

 <p>Ringer was married to Gladys Well on August 7, 1924. Gladys graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1923.  They had one daughter, Barbara Alice Ringer. </p>

 <p>William Ringer died October 4, 1973, in Washington, D.C.  He is buried in Clinton, North Carolina.</p>

</bioghist>


<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
 <p>The William R. Ringer papers document his time as a law student at the University of Michigan from September 1920 to June 1922.  The papers are organized into two series Diaries and Background. </p>
</scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>

<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Ringer, William Raimond, 1898-1973.</persname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. Law School.</corpname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.</corpname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.</corpname>

</controlaccess>








<controlaccess><genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Diaries.</genreform>

<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Photographs.</genreform></controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">

<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Background</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent> <p>Material in the Background series includes genealogical and biographical information supplied by the donor (a friend of Ringer's daughter) pertaining to William Ringer, his wife Gladys Wells, his brother Horace Thomas Ringer and his father Victor Howard Ringer.  Five copy prints (sent by the donor as digital e-mail attachments) feature photographs of Ringer, his wife, and his brothers.</p></scopecontent>
 <c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Biography</unittitle></did></c02>
 <c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Photographs</unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Diairies</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent> <p>The Diaries series consists of three volumes used by Ringer as a combination diary and scrapbook.  Ringer's diary entries are lengthy and well written containing observations of his impressions of the campus and town, course work, fellow students, social life and notable campus events. The entries are richest starting with his trip to Ann Arbor on September 27-28, 1920, and continuing through to February 25, 1922.  Scrapbook-type content includes newspaper clippings, tickets, programs, mementoes and some letters and official university documents tipped in alongside the corresponding diary entries. One particularly noteworthy item is the ticket for a "modern poets" lecture series appearance by poet Carl Sandberg on April 5, 1922, along with clippings concerning Sandberg's appearance. (Other poets in the series on the ticket include Padraic Collum, Lewis Untermeyer, Amy Lowell and Vachel Lindsay).</p></scopecontent>
 <c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume 10 (partial), <unitdate type="inclusive">September 27, 1920-March 8, 1921</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
 <c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume 11, <unitdate type="inclusive">March 9-December 6, 1921</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
 <c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume 12, <unitdate type="inclusive">December 8, 1921-June 1922</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>

</dsc>



<descgrp type="add"><relatedmaterial> <head>Related Material</head><p>Ringer numbered each of his diary volumes. The volumes covering the University of Michigan contain part of volume 10 and volumes 11 and 12. Volumes 1-9 and the first part of volume 10 were donated to Indiana University in Bloomington.  The earlier Ringer volumes and some additional content are part of the holdings of the Indiana University Archives. The finding aid for the content at Indiana may be accessed at this link:  http://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/findingaids/archives/InU-Ar-VAC1729  (link accessed 3 August 2012). </p></relatedmaterial></descgrp></archdesc>

</ead>
