<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"[]>
<ead>
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::ypsigt.xml//EN" encodinganalog="identifier">
umich-bhl-86417
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">Finding Aid for 
Ypsilanti Greek Theater Records, 1963-1967
</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Nika J. Kayne</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
        <date encodinganalog="date">
2005</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Thomas E. Powers, 
<date>April 2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date>20050425</date>
        <item>Original encoding from Word 6.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb />Bentley Historical Library<lb />University of Michigan</publisher>
      <titleproper>Finding aid for<lb />
Ypsilanti Greek Theater Records, 1963-1967</titleproper>
      <author>Finding aid created by<lb /> 
Nika J. Kayne, February 1993</author>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="marc21">
    <did>
      <origination>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110">
Ypsilanti Greek Theater
</corpname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="245">
Ypsilanti Greek Theater records
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1963-1967
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="300">
0.5 linear feet and 3 oversized volumes
</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <unitid encodinganalog="099" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
86417 Bp 2
</unitid>
      <langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language></langmaterial>
      <abstract>
Organization established in Ypsilanti, Michigan for the performance of Greek theater productions. Papers of theater president, Clara Owens; administrative files including minutes, correspondence, and financial records, printed material, press releases, clippings and scrapbooks, and photographs.
</abstract>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="852">
          <subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
        <extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload" />
      </repository>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admin">
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p>
The records (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">5497</num>) were a gift from Mrs. Clara Owens, former president of the Ypsilanti Greek Theater. They came to the library in 1974.  
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <p>
The record group is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <p>
Copyright has been transferred to the Regents of the University of Michigan.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
        <p>[item], folder, box,
Ypsilanti Greek Theater Records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p>
      </prefercite>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
      <p>The Ypsilanti Greek Theater, sometimes referred to as the Ypsilanti Greek Festival, was an organization existing roughly from 1963 to 1967, whose purpose was to bring about a revival of the ancient Greek dramatic tradition in Ypsilanti, Michigan.  Organizers constructed a theater in accordance with the designs of the traditional Greek amphitheater, and they produced a number of Greek dramas, attracting considerable local and national attention to the Ypsilanti area.</p>
      <p>The Ypsilanti Greek Theater was actually only a small part of "PROJECT 73,"  the title given to Ypsilanti's sesquicentennial celebration.  Designed in part to transform Ypsilanti into an economic, cultural, and educational center, the sesquicentennial did spur long-term plans to increase tourism, attract businesses, and create new educational facilities.  According to the town's boosters, Ypsilanti was to become an important midwestern economic and cultural center.</p>
      <p>As part of this vision, in 1963 a group of people organized, dedicating themselves to the revival of Greek drama.  They drew widespread support over the next two years and were able to construct a classical Greek theater in the Riverside Park area by the summer of 1965.  Much effort was expended as organizers solicited support and financial contributions from various local businesses, the city council, certain historical societies, and many larger sponsors including the Ford Foundation, and the federal government.  </p>
      <p>Alexis Solomos, former director of the Greek National Theater in Athens, became the new director, and many prominent local people served as officers including Mrs. Clara Owens, the president of the Ypsilanti Greek Theater.  Three dramas were successfully produced during the 1966 season including Aeschylus' <title render="italic">The Oresteia</title>.  Many well-known actors performed, including Melina Mercouri and Christopher Plummer.</p>
      <p>Despite its artistic success, the Ypsilanti Greek Theater failed after its first season due to monetary problems and mismanagement.  Mrs. Owens' relationship with the Board of Directors of the Ypsilanti Greek Theater was less than harmonious; a number of conflicts arose usually centered around administrative decisions and the management of finances.  For whatever reasons, the Theater closed after the 1967 season.  In retrospect, it would have been costly to maintain the Theater on a profitable foundation.  Nevertheless, the venture represents an interesting cultural experiment in the history of this largely blue collar community.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <p>The records of the Ypsilanti Greek Theater (0.5 linear feet and 3 volumes) range in dates from 1963 to 1967.  The bulk of the information covers only the years 1965-1967 and provides minimal information from 1963 and 1964.  Really the only materials that cover the earlier years of the organization are the scrapbooks.</p>
      <p>The collection consists mainly of the papers of former president of the organization, Mrs. Clara Owens.  Included are administrative records, photographs, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, and printed materials.  The papers have been divided into five series:  Personal Records, Clara Owens; Administrative; and Publicity and Other Related Materials.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <p>
        <extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload" />
      </p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Arts.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Theater--Michigan--Ypsilanti.</subject>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Ypsilanti Greek Theater.</corpname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Ypsilanti (Mich.)</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects - Visual Materials:</head>
        <subject source="lctgm" encodinganalog="650">Theaters--Michigan--Ypsilanti.</subject>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Ypsilanti Greek Theater.</corpname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Ypsilanti (Mich.)</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Contributors: </head>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Owens, Clara.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Architectural drawings.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Photographs.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Scrapbooks.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Personal Records, Clara Owens, <unitdate type="inclusive">1965-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Personal Records, Clara Owens series includes some comparative information about other theaters, a list of staff and patrons, and Mrs. Owens' office papers which are composed of organizational bylaws, building plans, administrative notes to herself, and several narratives written to explain the mission of the Ypsilanti Greek Theater, its staff, and its long-term plans.  Much of this latter material appears to have been for her own reference and is not meant to suggest a complete view of the workings of the organization.  It does however give a very good idea of the intention and philosophy of the founding members of the organization.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>Business Notes</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>Staff and Patrons</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>Other Theaters</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Administrative, <unitdate type="inclusive">1965-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Administrative series deals with all of the business matters of the organization including detailed financial information, weekly minutes of most meetings during the years 1965-1967, and a good deal of business and personal correspondence.  The Financial subseries, ranging from 1965 to 1967, consists of annual budgets, projected spending allowances, expenditure lists, payrolls, monetary allotments to different tasks, and sources of potential funds.  The Minutes subseries includes the weekly minutes from the meetings of the Board of Directors and minutes from different committee meetings.  Both of these folders document the detailed and daily business of the Ypsilanti Greek Theater, including many of the conflicts encountered.  The Correspondence subseries includes a series of Mrs. Owen's personal and business letters from various local businesses and patrons, as well as supportive notes from friends and relatives.  A great deal of general correspondence addressed to the Board of Directors can also be found here.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>Financial</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>Board of Directors</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>Committees (Steering Committee, Coordinating Committee, etc.)</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>Internal</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>External</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Publicity and other related materials</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Publicity and Other Related Materials includes three subseries. The Printed Materials subseries includes items such as pamphlets and brochures about Ypsilanti and the Greek Theater, as well as form letters meant to be sent out to everyone on the mailing list. Photographs includes a number of photographs of the officers and members of the organization as well as some of the plans for the theater. The Public Information subseries contains a number of press releases sent out by the office of Mrs. Owens regarding major announcements, a folder of loose newspaper clippings from various local papers, plus three oversized scrapbooks which fully document the founding and history of the organization in its early years.  These scrapbooks are a very good source of information for the years 1963-1965, a time period not well covered by the remainder of the material.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>Printed Materials, <unitdate type="inclusive">1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>
              <genreform normal="Photographs">Photographs</genreform>
            </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Press and Public Materials, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>Press Releases</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>Clippings</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="volume" label="Oversize Volume">1</container>
              <unittitle>
                <genreform normal="Scrapbooks">Scrapbooks</genreform>, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1965</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <extent>3 volumes</extent>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>