<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead><eadheader><eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="-//us::MiU-H//TEXT us::MiU-H::anatdona.xml//EN" encodinganalog="identifier">umich-bhl-950</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt>
<titleproper encodinganalog="title">Finding Aid for Anatomical Donations Program (University of Michigan) records, 1881-1990.</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="creator">Collection processed and finding aid prepared by Brian A. Williams, 1994</author></titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher><date encodinganalog="date">1994</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid prepared by Diane Silva<date>1997</date></creation></profiledesc>

<revisiondesc>
<change><date>199812</date><item>Converted to EAD version 1.0 using WORD 6 macro and some hand tagging.</item></change>
<change><date>199812</date><item>Converted to EAD version 1.0 using WORD 6 macro and some hand tagging.</item></change>
<change><date>June 15, 1997</date><item>Bill Landis, Finding aid updated to current BHL EAD encoding standards.</item></change>
<change><date>July 12, 1997</date><item>Bill Landis,  Second update after discussion with Greg Kinney.</item></change>
<change><date>8/9/1997</date><item>headings removed. GK</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage><publisher>University Archives Program <lb/>Bentley Historical Library <lb/>University of Michigan</publisher><titleproper>Finding Aid for <lb/>Anatomical Donations Program<lb/> (University of Michigan) <lb/>Records, <date>1881-1980</date></titleproper><author>Finding aid prepared by <lb/>Brian A. Williams, 1994</author></titlepage></frontmatter>

<archdesc level="recordgrp" type="inventory" audience="external" relatedencoding="marc21"><did>
<origination><corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110">University of Michigan. Anatomical Donations Program.</corpname></origination>
<unittitle encodinganalog="245">Anatomical Donations Program (University of Michigan) Records 
<unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive" normal="1881/1980">1881-1980</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">3.5 linear ft.</extent></physdesc>
<unitid label="Call No." encodinganalog="099" type="call number">950 Bimu 2</unitid>
<langmaterial>The materials are in <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">English.</language></langmaterial>
<abstract>Unit of the University of Michigan concerned with the procurement of cadavers for anatomical instruction, includes registers and permits detailing the acquisition and tracking of cadavers for medical instruction at  the University of Michigan</abstract>
<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea> University of Michigan</corpname><extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>The collection (Accession No.<num encodinganalog="541$e" type="donor">2937</num>) was received through the Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology in 1994.</p></acqinfo>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>The collection is open for research.</p></accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>Copyright to the collection has been transferred to the Regents of the Univerrsity of Michigan.</p></userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>item, folder title, Box No., Anatomical Donations Program Records, Bentley Historical Library,  University of Michigan.</p></prefercite></descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><p>Although the <corpname>Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology </corpname>has legally been receiving bodies since the latter part of the nineteenth century, the present <corpname>Anatomical Donations Program </corpname>was established in 1958, under Act 138 of the Public Acts of 1958 and modified as the Uniform Anatomical Gift Act (Act 189 of the Public Acts of 1969).</p><p>When the University of Michigan Medical School began instruction in 1850, the need for cadavers for practical study soon developed.  By 1852 practical anatomy was a requirement and dissection work one of the required laboratory courses.  During these early years it was incumbent upon the demonstrator of anatomy to supply the necessary cadavers.  Lacking any public law governing the procurement of bodies, the early history of the department of anatomy is rife with stories of grave-robbing and body-snatching.  As the available supply of bodies was exhausted, the demonstrator was forced to rely on outside agents to supply the needs of the Medical School.  These agents or "resurrectionists," often supplied the school with some rather infamous cadavers.</p><p>In 1867, the state of Michigan passed the first anatomical act, "authorizing the dissection in certain cases for the advancement of science," and provided that unclaimed bodies from state hospitals and prisons be provided to medical schools.  This act failed to provide any means of enforcement and was modified in 1875 to include penalties for non-compliance.</p><p>Despite the passage of legislation there remained a shortage of bodies for study.  In a report to the Board of Regents on July 28, 1880, anatomical demonstrator William Herdman addressed the on-going issue of grave-robbing.  In his report he specified the three levels of recourse for procuring bodies.  The first goal was to "exhaust all strictly legal sources of supply," followed by an effort "to complete the supply from the surplus at other colleges," and finally to "draw from the pauper and friendless dead at our county houses and asylums."  <bibref>(University of Michigan Medical School, <title render="italic">"Report on Grave Robbing,"</title> by  William Herdman, 1880, Box 135).</bibref></p><p>The 1875 act continued to be modified throughout the nineteenth century and into the early twentieth century.  It was not until 1958 that an entirely new anatomical act was passed.  Authored primarily by Russell T. Woodburne, chairman of the University of Michigan Department of Anatomy, the new act established an anatomical committee and created rules for the transportation, preservation and allocation of anatomical material.</p><p>Since 1958, the handling of anatomical material has been controlled by the State Anatomical Board in accordance with Michigan law.  The State Board consists of one appointed member from each of the four state institutions legally authorized to receive anatomical material and one ex-officio member from the Michigan Department of Public Health.</p><p>Currently the University of Michigan maintains an active file of over 18,000 enrollment forms from prospective donors.  Upon approval, cadavers accepted by the Medical School are given registry numbers and the majority of them are embalmed for future use in gross anatomy courses.  Following study, which may be up to 18 months after donation, individual cadavers are cremated and their ashes collected and stored in catalogued containers.  Families of donors have the option of having the ashes returned or may have them interred during the annual memorial service conducted by the Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Over the years the location of the memorial services has changed.  Information on interments prior to 1942 appears to be nonexistent.  Information on the location and approximate time periods of interments is given below:<chronlist>
<chronitem><date>1942-1963</date><event>Fairview Cemetery (1401 Wright St.)</event></chronitem>
<chronitem><date>1963-1987</date><event>United Memorial Gardens (4800 Curtis Road, Plymouth)</event></chronitem>
<chronitem><date>1988-     </date><event><corpname>Washtenong Memorial Park </corpname>(3771 Whitmore Lake Road)</event></chronitem>
</chronlist></p>

<p>For further information on the Department of Anatomy and the procurement of anatomical material the researcher is advised to consult the following:  <bibref>Huelke, Donald F., <title>"History of the Department of Anatomy The University of Michigan: Part I. 1850-1894."</title> <title render="italic">The University of Michigan Medical Bulletin</title>, Vol. 27, no. 1, Jan.-Feb. 1961 </bibref></p><p>For two detailed accounts of grave-robbing cases that involved the University of Michigan the researcher should consult the following: <bibref>Holtz, William, <title render="italic">"Jesse James and the Medical School: Bankrobbers, Burkers, and Bodysnatchers."</title>  Michigan Quarterly Review, Vol. VI, no. 2, April 1967 (pp. 90-98)</bibref><bibref>Sievers, Harry J.,<title render="italic">"The Harrison Horror,"</title> Public Library of Fort Wayne and Allen County, 1955.</bibref></p></bioghist>

<scopecontent><p>These records document the acquisition and tracking of  cadavers for  medical instruction at the  University of Michigan for nearly a century, beginning in 1881.  Although these records were created to fulfill an administrative need, researchers will find that the records contain an abundance of information.  In addition to the obvious  genealogical information,  quantitative and qualitative statistics on  causes of death and  ages of death can be extracted from these records.  This documentation also provides commentary on changing  social values, as the sources of  cadavers moved from unclaimed  paupers, to the development of program sustained by  voluntary donations.</p></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351"><p>The records are divided into the following series: <list type="simple"><item>Anatomical Materials Register, 1881-1974 (2 linear ft.)</item><item>Burial-Transit Permits, 1943-1980 (1.5 linear ft.)</item></list> </p></arrangement>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p>

<controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="611">University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy</corpname><subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Human anatomy</subject><subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Human dissection</subject><subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Registers of 
births, etc.--Michigan</subject></controlaccess></controlaccess>

<dsc type="combined">
<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Anatomical Materials Register, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1881/1974">1881-1974</unitdate></unittitle><physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">2 linear ft.</extent></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>Each incoming  cadaver was assigned a sequential  registry number by the  Medical School.  These numbers are recorded in a series of  ledgers beginning with number 1 on March 7, 1881 and ending with number 20,000 which was received on July 22, 1974.  This first series,  Anatomical Materials Register, consists of nine bound  ledgers and four loose leaf post binders that cover the period from 1881 to 1974.  Although the information contained in the  ledgers varies over time, these records typically include name, age, date of death,  cause of death, and method of shipment.  Occasionally the names of  physicians and relatives are supplied as is information on the  disposition of the body.  The entries are generally chronological although delays in shipping the  cadaver may translate into a juxtaposition of the chronology.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><unittitle><genreform>Ledgers</genreform></unittitle></did>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume I (1-1,858), <unitdate type="inclusive">March 7, 1881 - September 20, 1897</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume II (1,860-3,800), <unitdate type="inclusive">October 10, 1897 - July 18, 1916</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume III (3,801-5,800), <unitdate type="inclusive">July 21, 1916 - February 10, 1925</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume IV (5,801-7,790), <unitdate type="inclusive">February 10, 1925 - February 2, 1931</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume V (7,791-9,780), <unitdate type="inclusive">February 3, 1931 - January 8, 1937</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume VI (9,781-11,790), <unitdate type="inclusive">January 12, 1937 - March 6, 1941</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume VII (11,791-13,780), <unitdate type="inclusive">March 6, 1941 - May 12, 1947</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume VIII (13,781-15,769), <unitdate type="inclusive">May 13, 1947 - May 4, 1955</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Volume IX (15,770-16,521), <unitdate type="inclusive">May 4, 1955 - July 23, 1958</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><unittitle>Loose Leaf Binders</unittitle></did>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle>Volume X (16,515-17,489), <unitdate type="inclusive">July 24, 1958 - June 24, 1962</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle>Volume XI (17,490-18,347), <unitdate type="inclusive">June 29, 1962 - August 8, 1966</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle>Volume XII (18,348-19,249), <unitdate type="inclusive">August 12, 1966 - May 17, 1971</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle>Volume XIII (19,250-20,000), <unitdate type="inclusive">May 7, 1971 - July 22, 1974</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03></c02></c01>
<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Burial-Transit Permits, <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1943/1980">1943-1980</unitdate></unittitle><physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">1.5 linear ft.</extent></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>The Burial-Transit Permits, issued by the <corpname>Michigan Department of Health</corpname>, represent documentation that was required to accompany the remains during transportation.  The permits begin in January 1943 and end in 1975, with the exception of a separate sequence of baby burial-transit  permits that date from 1965 to 1980 (earlier baby burial-transit permits are interfiled with the regular permits).  These permits contain information that generally parallels that which is provided in the  anatomical materials register.  The  registry number appears on each of the   permits and can be cross referenced to the registry.  From 1943 to 1964 the  permits are sequentially arranged.  Beginning in 1965 the  permits are arranged alphabetically by name within each year.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><container label="Box" type="box">3</container><unittitle>Permits 12,436-16,390, <unitdate type="inclusive">January 1943 - December 1957</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container label="Box" type="box">4</container><unittitle>Permits 16,391-20,240, <unitdate type="inclusive">January 1958 - August 1975</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container label="Box" type="box">5</container><unittitle>Baby Permits (ca. 18,000-21,600), <unitdate type="inclusive">1965-1980 </unitdate></unittitle><note><p>(For earlier years baby  permits are interfiled with the general permits.)</p></note></did></c02></c01></dsc></archdesc></ead>