<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::barbeau.xml//EN" encodinganalog="identifier">
umich-bhl-86395
</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
Peter Barbeau Papers, 1789-1909
</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Bayliss Library staff </author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date">
2006 </date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Thomas E. Powers, 
<date>April 2006</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage></profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>20060428 </date><item>Original encoding from Word 6.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
Peter Barbeau Papers, 1789-1909</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Michigan Historical Collections staff</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>

<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">
Barbeau, Peter
</persname>
</origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
Peter Barbeau papers 
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1789-1909
</unitdate>

</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
8 microfilm rolls
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="099" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
86395; mf 501c-mf 508c
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
State representative from Chippewa County, Michigan. Correspondence and business papers dealing with mining, fishing, shipping, fur trading, lumbering and other businesses in the Northern Peninsula, particularly in Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan; also maritime papers, ships' manifests from Michilimackinac and Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan, miscellaneous American Fur Company papers, and papers on lighthouse administration, the Sault Ste. Marie Canal, and Republican politics.</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
The papers were microfilmed from originals located at the Bayliss Library in Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan. The microfilm rolls were acquired in 1959.</p></acqinfo>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>
The collection is open to research.
</p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
No copyright restrictions
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
Peter Barbeau Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>
</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>Peter B. Barbeau was a prominent merchant and community leader in Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan, during the nineteenth century. He was born June 29, 1800, in LaPrairie, Quebec, and died in the Sault on October 17, 1882. </p>

<p>Barbeau reputedly arrived in the Sault in 1817. He was initially employed by the Hudson's Bay Company, but eventually entered the service of John Jacob Astor's American Fur Company. After a tenure of company service in Baraboo, Wisconsin, he re-settled in Sault Ste. Marie in 1834. In the same year he was naturalized as a U.S. citizen at Mackinac, and indentured as a clerk under Gabriel Franchere (factor of the American Fur Company). </p>

<p>Barbeau continued in the employ of this company until 1842, when, after being refused an increase in salary, he resigned his position to embark upon his own commercial endeavors. He eventually opened a general store and trading post in Sault Ste. Marie and organized an extensive fishery on Lake Superior.</p>

<p>Archange LaLonde of the Sault and Barbeau were married around 1831. Two of three daughters survived to marry prominent area merchants. Henrietta married Myron W. Scranton, who purchased Barbeau's store in 1864. Flavia married James Pendill of Marquette, who had established a major sawmill west of the Sault as early as 1834.</p>

<p>In addition to Barbeau's commercial interests, he maintained an active career in civic affairs. He became a county commissioner in 1838. He was elected to the state legislature in 1842, and Register of Deeds in 1845. The following year he secured a county judgeship. In 1849 and again in 1879 he was elected village president of Sault Ste. Marie.</p>

<p>Barbeau was an early and effective advocate of the first shipping lock at Sault Ste. Marie, and when the second lock was opened in 1872, he presided over the dedication ceremonies. </p>

<p>During his years of residency in the Upper Peninsula, Barbeau acquired extensive holdings of property in the area. A log house at the corner of Barbeau Lane and Water Street served as the first Barbeau home and remained in the family until 1895. He purchased and resided in the former Indian Agency house, previously the residence of Henry Schoolcraft. He owned and took possession of Chippewa Street, which was later changed to Barbeau. The settlement of Barbeau, its post office and Barbeau Point were named after him. Bass Lodge, built on Neebish Island ca. 1850, remained in the family until 1873. He also operated trading posts at Grand Marais and LaPointe on Lake Superior. </p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>This collection of eight microfilm rolls divides into two series: Correspondence and business papers, and Maritime papers. Although titled the Peter Barbeau collection, the papers are of Barbeau and others Northern Michigan businessmen.  The papers detail business activities, particularly in Sault Ste. Marie area and concern mining, fishing, shipping, fur trading, lumbering, and other businesses.  Also included are maritime papers consisting of customs papers and ships manifest from Michilimackinac and Sault Ste. Marie.  Found within the collection as well are miscellaneous American Fur Company papers, papers on lighthouse administration, the Sault Ste. Marie Canal, and some Republican politics.</p>
</scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>

<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">American Fur Company.</corpname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Barbeau, Peter.</persname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Bridges.</subject>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Burt, Hiram Austin, b. 1839.</persname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Business records.</subject>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Chippewa County (Mich.)</geogname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Cleveland-Cliffs Iron Company.</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Fishing--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Fur trade--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Indians of North America--Michigan.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Lighthouses--Michigan.</subject>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.</persname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Logging--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Lumbering--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.</subject>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Mackinac Island (Mich.)</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Marquette (Mich.)</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Upper Peninsula (Mich.)</geogname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Michilimackinac Company.</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Mines and mineral resources--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.</subject>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Moore, William P., 1787-1850.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Pendill, James, 1812-1885.</persname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Republican Party (Mich.)</corpname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.)</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">Sault Sainte Marie Canal (Mich.)</geogname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Scranton, William Warren, 1917-</persname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Shipping--Great Lakes (North America).</subject>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Trowbridge, L. S. (Luther Stephen), 1836-1912.</persname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">United States. Bureau of Customs.</corpname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.</geogname>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Whig Party (U.S.)</corpname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Whiting, Justin Rice, 1847-1903.</persname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess><head>Contributors: </head>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Baraga, Frederic, 1797-1868.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Haring, Samuel K.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Mack, Stephen, 1762-1826.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">McKnight, Thomas.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">McMath, John Watson, b. 1824.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Scranton, Myron W.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Wendell, Jacob A. T., 1826-1879.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">White, Peter, 1830-1908.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Whittemore, Gideon Olin, 1800-1863.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Woodbridge, William, 1780-1861.</persname>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">


<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Correspondence and business papers</unittitle></did>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">October 1, 1789-1853</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(There are few early items; the papers really begin in 1844.  Included is considerable material on light house administration, four brief letters of Frederick Baraga, and some material on mining and shipping.)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">2</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1853/1864">1853-1864</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(Most of the correspondence on this reel is with James P. Pendill, Barbeau's son-in-law, William P. Moore of Detroit, Wm. W. Scranton of Detroit, and J.S. Whiting of Detroit, on business matters involving Barbeau.  There are also letters written by Barbeau during the winter of 1858-1859 which he spent in Detroit.  There are nine letters from Bishop Baraga of a trivial nature, some correspondence, 1858, of J.A.T. Wendell and of John McMath, 1864, both collectors of customs at the Sault; and scattered material on shipping, mining, fishing and lumber in the Upper Peninsula; also some correspondence on firs.  There is one letter from Peter White of a routine nature, and some interesting comments on the Civil War's effect on business in 1861.)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">3</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1864/1909">1864-1909</unitdate> and miscellaneous </unittitle></did> <note><p>(Until 1869 most of the correspondence on this reel is with Barbeau; from 1869 to 1880 the correspondence is with Myron W. Scranton who became postmaster at the Sault in that year and was also in business there; after 1880 the papers seem to be of Gilmore G. Scranton, son of Myron Scranton.  Correspondents of these three are Scranton, J.T. Whiting, L.S. Trowbridge, J.P. Pendill, Hiram A. Burt, and Stephen Mack.  The correspondence concerns various business interests including the fur trade, fishing, shipping, mining, the St. Mary's ship canal, customs' affairs and some local Republican politics, especially in 1870)</p></note></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Maritime papers</unittitle></did>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">4</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1803/1831">1803-1831</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(The papers on this reel are mostly customs papers and ships' manifests from Michilimackinac; some are of the Michilimackinac Company, others are of the American Fur Company.)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">5</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1832/1838">1832-1838</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(Customs papers and ships' manifests from Michilimackinac)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">6</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1838/1852">1838-1852</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(Customs records and ships' manifests from Michilimackinac until 1846; after that date most of the papers pertain to Sault Ste. Marie)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">7</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1852/1856">1852-1856</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(Mostly ships' manifests from Sault Ste. Marie, with a few from Michilimackinac; also lists of vessels cleared at the Sault and at Green Bay)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="reel" label="Roll">8</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1856/1883">1856-1883</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(Mostly ships' manifests from the Sault)</p></note></c02></c01>


</dsc></archdesc>

</ead>