<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::blumnan.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-2014133</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
Coming Out Whole Conference collection

</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Claire De Witt </author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2014">
2014</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Olga Virakhovskaya, 
<date>2014</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
<descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
</profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2014-10-03</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2010 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
Coming Out Whole Conference Collection, 1986</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Claire De Witt, September 2014</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>
 

<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">
Blum, Nancy, collector</persname>
</origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
Coming Out Whole Conference collection<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1986
</unitdate>
 

</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
0.6 linear feet</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
2014133 Aa 2
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
The Coming Out Whole conference was held in April of 1986 with a goal of addressing challenges faced by lesbians with addictions.  The conference was held in Ann Arbor, MI and was sponsored by the University of Michigan's Lesbian and Gay Male Programs Office.  The collection includes planning materials, conference materials, and evaluations of the conference including video recordings of select sessions.
</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
The record group was received from Nancy Blum (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">10790</num>) in May 2012.</p></acqinfo>
 
<accruals encodinganalog="584"><p>
No further additions to the records are expected.
</p></accruals>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>
The collection is open to research.
</p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
Coming Out Whole Conference collection, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>

 

</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>The Coming Out Whole conference was held in April of 1986 with a goal of addressing challenges faced by lesbians with addictions.  The specific challenges that lesbians faced in dealing with addictions had not been addressed at the University of Michigan previously, and as more women came out as lesbians there was a greater need for lesbian-specific resources for coping with addictions.  Addictions addressed at the conference included those related to drugs, alcohol, food, anger, and sex/relationships.  </p>

<p>Each panel session took on a different addiction through a variety of methods; some facilitators spoke about their own personal experiences, others asked participants to share with each other what their experiences with addiction were.  At the end of the conference participants were asked to evaluate the sessions that they attended, which resulted in a comprehensive evaluation for the conference as a whole. </p>

<p>The conference was designed by Nancy Blum who served as the Programs Co-Coordinator for the Lesbian and Gay Male Programs Office at the University of Michigan.  Blum worked as a therapist with clients in the Lesbian and Gay Male Programs Office as well as an advocate for local programs offered in the Ann Arbor, MI area for lesbians and gay males.  The Lesbian and Gay Male Programs Office at the University of Michigan was the successor organization to the Office of Human Sexuality in the 1980s and a precursor to the Spectrum Center.  The Office was founded because of student, faculty, and staff advocacy and focused on providing support for gay and lesbian individuals on campus.  Activities included individual therapy, group programs, as well as raising awareness of resources available in Ann Arbor, MI.  </p>

</bioghist>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<p>
The record group consists of three series: Pre-Conference Materials, Conference Materials, and Post-Conference Materials.</p>
 
</arrangement>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>The Coming Out Whole Conference records document the challenges faced by lesbians who have addictions or loved ones struggling with addictions as well as strategies and challenges to overcoming these issues.  The collection will be used by those seeking information on the relationship between sexuality and addictions or exploring how the lesbian community addressed addiction in the mid-1980s. </p></scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>

<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">Coming Out Whole Conference.</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Gay college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Homosexuality--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Lesbians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Lesbians--Substance use.</subject>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. Lesbian-Gay Male Program Office.</corpname>
</controlaccess>


<controlaccess><head>Genre Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Video recordings.</genreform></controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">
<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Pre-Conference Materials</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The Pre-Conference Materials series include planning notes, preliminary budgets, and brainstorm material related to the development of the conference.  This series also contains material related to Nancy Blum's role as Programs Co-Coordinator for the Lesbian and Gay Male Programs Office at the University of Michigan, with documentation of meetings for various lesbian groups in the area. </p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Nancy Blum Programs Co-Coordinator for the Lesbian and Gay Male Programs Office Materials</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Conference Correspondence</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Conference Planning Outlines</unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Conference Materials</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The Conference Materials series document the events of the Coming Out Whole conference.  It includes a conference program listing panels and sessions as well as notes from facilitators for various sessions.  This series also contains video recordings for select sessions and release forms for those recorded.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Speaker Notes, </unittitle></did> <note><p>(Including notes from  speakers Jean Swallow and Judith Boston)</p></note></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Video Recordings of Select Sessions, </unittitle> <physdesc><physfacet>4 VHS video cassettes</physfacet></physdesc></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Video Release Forms</unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Post Conference Materials</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The Post-Conference Materials series consists primarily of evaluations of the conference from the perspective of participants.  These include each individual response as well as a record of all evaluations combined and separated by session.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Conference Evaluations</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Final Conference Budget</unittitle></did></c02></c01>


</dsc>
<descgrp type="add"><relatedmaterial><head>Related Material</head><p>
For related materials see the finding aid for <title render="italic" linktype="simple" href="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/b/bhlead/umich-bhl-02139" show="replace" actuate="onrequest">Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs (University of Michigan) 1976-1997.</title></p>



</relatedmaterial></descgrp>




</archdesc>

</ead>