<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::chipmanf.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-86990</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
Chipman family papers, 1925-1964

</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Anne E. Zald, 1985</author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2006">
2006</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Thomas E. Powers, 
<date>November 2006</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
<descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
</profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2006-11-09</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2000 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
Chipman family papers, 1925-1964</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Anne E. Zald, March 1985</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>

<famname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">
Chipman family
</famname>
</origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
Chipman family papers 
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1925-1964
</unitdate>

</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
2.3 linear feet 
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
86990 Aa 2
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
Chipman family of Ann Arbor, Michigan. Hope Chipman was a teacher at University School of the University of Michigan. Letters of sisters Hope and Dorothy; also letters exchanged with their mother Janet Chipman; and photographs.</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
The collection was the gift of Dorothy Chipman (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">5504</num>) and Hope Chipman (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">5584</num>).</p></acqinfo>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>
The collection is open to research.
</p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
Chipman family papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>
</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>Dorothy (b. 1896) and Hope Chipman (1900-1982), the principle correspondents in this collection, were born in Ames, Iowa.  Their mother, variously addressed as Jean or Janet, is also represented in the correspondence.  As children, the sisters lived in a variety of places as their father made his living in the early automotive industry.  In 1907 the family moved to Constantine, Michigan where the father worked for a firm which made magnetos.  In 1912 the family moved to Ann Arbor where he worked for a truck manufacturer, Annacar.  In 1923 they returned to Ames.</p>

<p>Dorothy and Hope Chipman each graduated from the University of Michigan.  Their brothers, Edgar and James (dates unknown), attended Iowa State University.  In 1925, when this collection begins, Hope enrolled at Columbia University to pursue a Master's Degree.  In May 1926 she received and accepted an offer to teach in Ann Arbor at University High School.  Dorothy was living in Ames with their mother and working in the business manager's office at Iowa State College.  In 1926 she moved to Rochester, New York where she was employed by the Eastman-Kodak Corporation.  Dissatisfied with her situation she joined Hope in Ann Arbor in 1927 and worked at the William L. Clements Library.  Their mother joined them in Ann Arbor, becoming a member of the First Presbyterian Church, while their brothers married.  James settled in New Jersey with his wife Georgia and daughter Ellen Janet, working as an engineer.  Edgar was an owner/operator of a gas and service station in Ypsilanti, Michigan, where he lived with his wife Katherine and children John and Janet.</p>

<p>In 1936-1937 Hope went to Spokane, Washington as an exchange teacher.  In 1939 she again entered an educational program, this time in Ames, Iowa, to study food preparation and management.  Dorothy spent the summer of 1940 at the University of Michigan Biological Station in Cheboygan, Michigan where she pursued an interest in jewelry making.  In 1949 the sisters moved to Everett, Washington for a year to ease the effects of Dorothy's allergies.  Ann Arbor remained their home, however until their retirement.  Dorothy and Hope each took summer vacations individually and together during which they traveled through various regions of the United States.  In 1962 they toured Europe together.  Each of their trips, and indeed at each step of their lives, they shared events and perceptions in their correspondence.</p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>The Chipman Papers are predominantly correspondence, with photographs and newspaper clippings as occasional enclosures.  There is also a series of photograph albums. The letters are arranged in three series for the major correspondents, Dorothy, Hope, and Jean Chipman.  Chronological arrangement of each series does reveal gaps.  Because the sisters lived together or with their mother for most of the period covered by the collection, it is only reasonable for their correspondence to illuminate those times (vacations, work assignments) when they were apart.  During those periods when they did correspond, they did so on a daily basis.  Correspondence from their brothers and other family members or friends is more sporadic.  The content of the letters is largely descriptive of the daily events of their lives, occasionally mentioning co-workers, work environments, and more rarely, events in the world-at-large.</p>





</scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. University School.</corpname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess><head>Contributors: </head>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Chipman, Dorothy, 1896-</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Chipman, Hope, 1900-1982.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Chipman, Janet.</persname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess><head>Genre Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Photographs.</genreform>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">


<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Dorothy Chipman</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Dorothy Chipman series includes letters (many with newspaper clippings as enclosures), postcards and occasional telegrams, arranged chronologically, and received from the following correspondents: Hope Chipman, especially 1925-1926, describing life and graduate work at Columbia University; Jean Chipman, especially 1936-1937, while visiting Hope in Spokane, Washington; and other family members and friends.  A run of letters dated 1933-1936, from Ossian L. Cook, addressed as Craig, discuss various topics, especially astrology and the works of Evangeline Adams.  Family photographs are attached as enclosures to the item dated July 11, 1939.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Letters to, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1925/1964">1925-1964</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>4 folders and 1 expandable folder</extent></physdesc></did> <note><p>(most letters still in envelopes)</p></note></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Hope Howland Chipman</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Hope Howland Chipman series includes letters (many with newspaper clipping enclosures), postcards, and telegram, arranged chronologically, and addressed to Hope, either individually or jointly, from Dorothy and Jean Chipman. These letters describe life in Ann Arbor while Hope was teaching in Spokane, Washington 1936-37. There are also letters from Marion McKinney describing events at University High School; from Edgar and James Chipman and their families, especially from 1949 when living with Dorothy in Everett, Washington; mimeographed letters from Preston and Lucy Slosson describing their vacation in Wyoming 1949; and letters received and sent during Hope and Dorothy's tour of Europe in 1962.  Photographs of Hope in a classroom are attached as enclosures to the item dated February 2, 1937.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><unittitle>Letters to</unittitle></did>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1924/1926">1924-1926</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1930/1934">1930-1934</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">September 1936-June 1937</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>2 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1938">1938</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1942/1944">1942-1944</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">July 1949-November 1950</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>2 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1952/1960">1952-1960</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">June-August 1962</unitdate> European tour</unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">June-August 1962</unitdate> European tour, outgoing correspondence</unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">October-November 1964</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Various dates</unittitle></did></c03></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle>Diary, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1934/1935">1934-1935</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Jean (Janet) Chipman</unittitle></did>
<scopecontent><p>The Jean (Janet) Chipman series includes letters, postcards, and telegrams addressed individually or jointly to Jean Chipman, and arranged chronologically.  From children, friends, and various family members, the items are descriptive of the following periods and events: Hope's social life and coursework at Columbia University, 1925-26; Dorothy's life and work for Eastman-Kodak, in Rochester, New York, 1926-27; items from her brother Ed regarding the hardships of the Depression, 1930-35; the family lives of her sons, especially 1930-35 and 1944-46; items from Hope in Spokane, Washington describing her experience as an exchange teacher, 1936-37; and Dorothy's trip West which included a visit at the Unity Training School in Lee's Summit, Missouri.  Photographs are enclosed with the following items: April 20, 1926 of Hope, James and family; April 23, 1927; September 18, 1936 of landscape and building of the Grand Coulee Dam; and December 31, 1944, of a relative's child.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><unittitle>Letters to</unittitle></did>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">July 1925-May 1927</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>4 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1930-March 1937</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">March 1937-October 1946</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>2 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1930/1949" certainty="approximate">1930s-1940s</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>1 expandable folder</extent></physdesc></did> <note><p>(letters still in envelopes)</p></note></c03></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous and unidentified</unittitle></did>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle>Various dates and recipients</unittitle></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle><genreform normal="Photographs">Photographs</genreform></unittitle></did>
<c02 level="file"><did><unittitle>Hope Chipman</unittitle></did>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">3</container><unittitle>Album, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1930/1943">1930-1943</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(University School students and class activities)</p></note></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">3</container><unittitle>Albums, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1938/1960">1938-1960</unitdate> </unittitle></did> <note><p>(class portraits and candid photographs)</p></note></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">3</container><unittitle>Album of class portraits, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1946">1946</unitdate></unittitle></did></c03>
<c03 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">3</container><unittitle>Informal photograph and miscellaneous</unittitle></did></c03></c02></c01>


</dsc></archdesc>

</ead>