<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "../fa-s-drive/ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::kalisch.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-2014135</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for 
Beatrice J. and Philip Kalisch papers 
</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Claire De Witt </author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2014">
2014</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Olga Virakhovskaya, 
<date>2014</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
<descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
</profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2014-10-03</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2010 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>Michigan Historical Collections<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
Beatrice J. and Philip Kalisch papers, 1969-1976</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Claire De Witt, September 2014</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>
 

<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">
Kalisch, Beatrice J.
</persname>
</origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
Beatrice J. and Philip Kalisch papers  
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1969-1976
</unitdate>
 
</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
3 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
2014135 Aa 2; UAm
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
Between 1969 and 1976 Beatrice and Philip Kalisch completed a series of interviews for what would become a three volume report titled <title render="italic"> From Training to Education: The Impact of Federal Aid on Schools of Nursing in the United States during the 1940's</title> (1974).  Transcripts of nterviews with men and women active in the field of nursing, specifically in an administrative position, during the 1940s including the Cadet Nurse Corps and associated programs under Lucile Petry Leone, the founding director of the Cadet Nurse Corps in 1943.</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
The record group was received from Beatrice J. Kalisch (donor no.<num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">10609</num>) in August 2011.</p></acqinfo>
 
<accruals encodinganalog="584"><p>
No further additions to the records are expected.
</p></accruals>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><p>
The collection is open to research.
</p></accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
Beatrice J. and Philip Kalisch papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>

 

</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>Beatrice and Philip Kalisch conducted numerous interviews in the late 1960s and into the 1970s regarding the training and education of nurses during the 1940s in America, specifically in the Cadet Nurse Corps.  This research resulted in a three-volume report titled<title render="italic"> From Training to Education: The Impact of Federal Aid on Schools of Nursing in the United States during the 1940's</title> .  </p>

<p>With the start of World War II many trained and experienced nurses went to Europe to help with the war effort.  This mass movement left a nursing shortage in the United States creating a higher demand for young women to receive training as nurses.  In June of 1943 the Bolton Act, proposed by Ohio congresswoman Frances Payne Bolton was passed by Congress creating the Cadet Nurse Corps.  The Cadet Nurse Corps was designed to provide training for nurses in the United States through subsidized tuition and expedited programs and was directed by Lucile Petry under the United States Public Health Service.  </p>

<p>A major component of the campaign to recruit more nurses was changing the way that nursing was viewed by the general public.  Advertisements paid for by the program called the Cadet Nurse Corps an opportunity to get a career for free; the Cadet Nurse was a "girl with a future."  By making nursing a reputable career for women the Cadet Nurse Corps was able to attract more girls into their training programs.</p>

<p>The Cadet Nurse Corps also provided funds to schools with nursing programs.  These funds were distributed by an administrative employee of the Cadet Nurse Corps, often a nurse herself, who visited the program to ensure that it was up to par with the requirements.  Through this standardization in nurse training the profession of nursing began to develop.</p>
</bioghist>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<p>
The record group consists of two series: Interviews and Research Materials.</p>
</arrangement>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>The Beatrice J. Kalisch Papers will be most useful for those interested in the administration of the Cadet Nurse Corps during the 1940s.  The Cadet Nurse Corps was responsible for training nurses during the 1940s to help bridge the gap left by nurses sent to Europe.  With the Cadet Nurse Corps also came a change in the perception of nursing to a respectable career for young women.  The papers document the experiences of the nurse or person interviewed during the 1940s and interviews were conducted between 1969 and 1976. </p>
</scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>

<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Bolton, Frances Payne Bingham, 1885-1977.</persname>
<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Leone, Lucile Petry, 1902-1999.</persname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Nurses--United States--Interviews.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Nursing--Study and teaching--United States.</subject>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">United States. Cadet Nurse Corps.</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">World War, 1939-1945--History.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">World War, 1939-1945--Women--United States.</subject>

</controlaccess>
 

<controlaccess><head>Contributors: </head>

<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Kalisch, Philip Arthur.</persname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess><head>Genre Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Audiotapes.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Interviews.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Photographs.</genreform>

</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined">
<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Interviews</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The Interviews series includes 101 interviews that Beatrice and Philip Kalisch performed in writing their report arranged in alphabetical order within each box.  Each interview is contained in an individual folder.  Some interviews were recorded on the five reel-to-reel audiotapes included.  Of particular note are three written and one recorded interview with Lucile Petry Leone and one recorded interview with retired Congresswoman Frances Payne Bolton.</p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">1</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969/1976">1969-1976</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>53 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969/1976">1969-1976</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>40 folders</extent></physdesc><note><p>(including a 1975 interview with Lucile Petry Leone)</p></note></did></c02>

<c02 level="item"><did><container type="box" label="Box">3</container><unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969/1976">1969-1976</unitdate> </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>8 folders  </extent></physdesc><note><p>(including a 1972 and a 1973 interview with Lucille Petry Leone)</p></note></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">2</container><unittitle>Recorded Interviews, (including those with Lucile Petry Leone and Frances Payne Bolton)</unittitle><physdesc><extent>5 reel-to-reel audio recordings</extent></physdesc></did></c02></c01>



<c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Research Materials <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1940/1950">1940-1950</unitdate></unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The Research Materials series contains material related to nursing in the 1940s.  This includes advertisements calling for nurses, correspondence between some of the program organizers and the Public Health Service, as well as pamphlets, guides, and other printed material created in the 1940s to encourage nursing as a profession.  Also included in the series is an oversize undated photograph portrait of an unidentified Nurse Cadet and oversize program advertisements. </p></scopecontent>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="box" label="Box">3</container><unittitle>Pamphlets, Advertisements, Correspondence, Guides </unittitle> <physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="folder" label="Folder"> 1</container><unittitle>Advertisements</unittitle></did></c02>
<c02 level="file"><did><container type="folder" label="Folder"> 1</container><unittitle>Photograph, unidentified, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>


</dsc></archdesc>

</ead>