<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::offclpub.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier">
umich-bhl-02135</eadid>

<filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for University of Michigan Official Publication 

</titleproper>
<author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by 
Bentley Library Staff</author></titlestmt>

<publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
<date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2013">
2013</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Encoded finding aid created by 
Greg Kinney, 
<date>2013</date></creation>

<langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in  <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage><descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules></profiledesc>

<revisiondesc><change><date>2013-07-05</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2007 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>

<frontmatter><titlepage>

<publisher>University Archives and Records Program<lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>

<titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/>
University of Michigan Official Publication 
</titleproper>

<author>Finding aid created by<lb/> 
Bentley Library Staff
</author>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21"><did>

<origination>
<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110">
University of Michigan Official Publication 
</corpname></origination>

<unittitle encodinganalog="245">
University of Michigan Official Publication
<unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">
1900-1971
</unitdate>
</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">
72 volumes
</extent></physdesc>

<unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number">
02135 Bimu C2 2
</unitid>

<langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>

<abstract>
Official Publications, 1900-1971, of the University of Michigan; bound sequentially in 72 volumes.
</abstract>


<repository><corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
<extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></repository></did>

<descgrp type="admin">
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><p>
ACQUISITON
<num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">NO.</num>
 
</p></acqinfo>

<accruals encodinganalog="584"><p>No further additions to the records are expected.</p></accruals>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
<p>The collection is open without restriction.</p>

<p><extptr href="uarpacc" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p></accessrestrict>


<userestrict encodinganalog="540"><p>
Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan
</p></userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524"><p>[item], folder, box,
University of Michigan Official Publication, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>


</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
<p>The University of Michigan Regents authorized publication of the first <title render="italic">Catalogue</title> in 1843.  For over six decades, this and the other principal official publications were produced through the efforts of various committees, faculty, and students without formal assignment to any specific unit or individual.</p>

<p>Later in the century, Professor William Henry Pettee served as editor of the official publications for a number of years until his death in 1904.  The President's report to the Board of Regents in September 1904 noted that, "For years he (Pettee) has been of the greatest service to the University in fields quite apart from his teaching, namely, as auditor of the accounts of the University and as editor of its official publications, the Calendar and Departmental Announcements . . . His minute acquaintance with our statutes, usages and traditions, and his proverbial accuracy as compiler and proof-reader, made our publications models of their kind."</p>

<p>Thereafter, two other faculty members assumed interim editorship of the official publications, Assistant Professor Louis A. Strauss (1904-1905) and Assistant Professor Henry A. Sanders (1907-1908).</p>

<p>Responsibility for editing and publishing Official Publications were first assigned to the Registrar in 1908, when Arthur Graham Hall returned to the University of Michigan faculty under the title Registrar of the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts and Editor of the University Publications.  In 1919, the Regents declined to appoint an independent "University editor to have charge of all catalogues and announcements and similar printed matter issued by the University."  Instead, Graham continued in the position of Registrar and Editor until his death in 1925, although Professor John W. Bradshaw was assigned to edit the <title render="italic">Catalogue</title> in 1922, due to Hall's ongoing illnesses.  Upon the appointment of Ira Melville Smith as Registrar in 1925, the Regents made supervision of the editing of "(t)he various University announcements and bulletins and the University catalogue" one of his five official duties.</p>

<p>The University of Michigan Official Publications have appeared under multiple, overlapping titles.  In 1915, a committee on nomenclature appointed by the Regents renamed the <title render="italic">Calendar of the University of Michigan...</title> as the <title render="italic">Catalogue of the University of Michigan ...</title> At the same time, the committee on nomenclature approved <title render="italic">Announcement</title> as the name for the publication of each school or college, and <title render="italic">Bulletin</title> for that of a program or smaller group within a school or college.  These names were not always used consistently, however.  Other titles included <title render="italic">University Bulletin</title> (used roughly from 1900 to 1925), <title render="italic">University of Michigan Bulletin</title> (first used circa 1925), and <title render="italic">University of Michigan Official Publication</title> (first used circa 1926, used consistently after 1928).  The changes in title did not appear at definite dates; older and newer titles frequently coincided in the same volumes.  In all cases, the contents included announcements, registers, reports, and miscellaneous items considered "official," but did not generally include the scholarly publications produced by units throughout the University.</p>

<p>With the creation of the University Press in 1930-1931, Official Publications were brought under the same authority as scholarly publications for the first time.  A Committee on Official Publications, consisting of the Registrar, the Managing Editor of the Press and a faculty representative, was created within the University Press organization.  Under this arrangement, the University Press was "primarily a co-ordinating and distributing agency," while other functions remained elsewhere in the university structure.  This included editorial duties for official publications, which continued to be handled by the Registrar's office through its Editorial Division.</p>

<p>In 1936, Walter Arthur Donnelley, who was already Editor of Museums Publications, was also named Supervising Editor of Publications in the Registrar's Office.  Under his supervision, the Registrar's Office was responsible for editing the Regents' <title render="italic">Proceedings</title>, the various student and faculty <title render="italic">Registers</title>, the annual <title render="italic">University of Michigan Directory</title>, and several scholarly series, including <title render="italic">Michigan Governmental Studies</title>, <title render="italic"/>  School of Forestry and Conservation <title render="italic">Bulletins</title> and <title render="italic">Circulars</title>, and <title render="italic">Ars Islamica</title>.  </p>

<p>The Office of Official Publications was finally removed from the Registrar's purview and added to the University Press's organizational and budgetary structure in 1945, though the Registrar remained chairman <title render="italic">ex oficio</title> of the University Committee on Official Publications.  In 1954, the role of the Registrar in official publications was further reduced when the Regents reorganized the committee, and the Vice President for Student Affairs was named chairman.</p>

<p>In 1963, an Ad Hoc Committee on University Publications Problems was convened to perform a survey of publications then in existence.  The Committee's 1964 final report recommended, among other things, "that the University Publications Office become the focal point for a concerted effort to establish University-wide editorial and production standards for its non-scholarly publications," which had become highly decentralized.  Of the 23 Publications listed in Appendix C to the report, "University of Michigan Official Publications, 1962-1963," only three, <title render="italic">General Information Announcement</title>, <title render="italic">Michigan Quarterly Review</title>, and <title render="italic">General Register</title> listed the Publications Office as the "Sponsoring Unit."</p>

<p>The Official Publications series ended in 1971.  It is not entirely clear why this occurred, but it is likely that with functional autonomy of an increasing number of academic units and increasing advancements in publication and duplication technologies, the need and desire for centralized Official Publications decreased.</p>


<p>------------------------</p>
<p>Sources</p>

<p>The University of Michigan, an encyclopedic survey, Volume I, Part I (1942), Wilfred B. Shaw, editor. Pages 241-263.</p>

<p>The University of Michigan, an encyclopedic survey, Volume IV, Part VIII (1958), Wilfred B. Shaw, editor. Pages 1413-1420.</p>

<p>The Proceedings of the Board of Regents (1817-1920), pages 654 and 748.</p>

<p>"University of Michigan Official publication Variations in Title," from the Official Publication collection, folder of loose documents including title list.</p>

<p>Final report to Vice President Roger W. Heyns from Ad Hoc Committee on University Publication Problems, May 8, 1964.</p>

</bioghist>



<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
<p>The 72 bound volumes of Official Publications  contain announcements, bulletins, reports and other printed material issued by various units and officers of the University, which were designated official publications.  Each volume corresponds to roughly one school year, as detailed in the attached list.  The individual publications were numbered sequentially, in order of publication, and are bound in numerical order.  Each publication also has a distinctive title, in addition to a volume and number.   Prior to about 1921 the annual bound set consisted almost exclusively of the Bulletins of  various schools and colleges.  After that date the bound set began to include additional publications such  the President's Report, financial reports, and   incidental publications such as the guide to Freshmen and reports on sponsored conferences and programs </p><p>The following numbers are missing, and their contents have not been determined:<list type="simple">
<item>1916-17  -- vol. 18 -- no. 6, 19, 21, 30, 41</item>
<item>1917-18 - -vol. 19 -- no. 7, 9, 11, 13, 27</item>
<item>1963-64 -- vol. 65 -- no. 20</item>
<item>1964-65 -- vol. 66 -- no. 20, 25, 73</item>
</list>
</p>


</scopecontent>

<controlaccess><p><extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/></p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head>

<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan--Periodicals.</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Universities and colleges--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Periodicals.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Education, Higher--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Periodicals.</subject>

</controlaccess>










</controlaccess>


<dsc type="combined"><c01><did><unittitle>Official Publications</unittitle></did><c02><did><unittitle>University Bulletin, Vol. 1,  no. 1- Vol. 29, no. 7, <unitdate>1900- August  13, 1927</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02><c02><did><unittitle>University of Michigan Official Publication, Vol. 29, no.8 - Vol.. 71, no. 98, <unitdate>August 20, 1927-March 5, 1971</unitdate></unittitle></did></c02></c01>

</dsc>
<descgrp type="add"><relatedmaterial><head>Related Material</head><p>A complete title list, in order of publication, for volumes 1-30 is available with the collection.</p>

<p>A card index is available for volumes 21-45, 48-65 and 67-72.  The card index is arranged by publishing unit, and alphabetically by subunit or title within each section, with the exception of Summer Session material, which is all under that heading.  The headings used in the card index, which may not correspond to current University organization, are:<list type="simple">
<item>Architecture</item>
<item>Business Administration</item>
<item>Dentistry</item>
<item>Education</item>
<item>Engineering</item>
<item>Extension</item>
<item>Law</item>
<item>Literature, Science and the Arts</item>
<item>Medical</item>
<item>Medical School. Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine</item>
<item>Music</item>
<item>Natural Resources</item>
<item>Nursing</item>
<item>Other Units</item>
<item>Pharmacy</item>
<item>Public Health</item>
<item>Rackham</item>
<item>Summer Session</item>
<item>Summer Session: Engineering Summer Conferences</item>
<item>Summer Session: Intensive Courses for Engineers</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Official Publications have been accessioned and preserved as part of university record groups on an irregular basis.  Therefore, researchers looking for official publications from a particular college, department, or unit should also consult that group's records and/or publications collections.</p>

<p>Finally, some Official Publications have been catalogued as individual items in the University of Michigan's library catalog system, Mirlyn, which Researchers should also consult.</p>
</relatedmaterial>



</descgrp>
</archdesc>



</ead>